<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-jbaptist_birth">
  <title>You will be silent, unable to speak</title>
  <epigraph>
    <attribution><emphasis>Luke 1:19-20</emphasis></attribution>
    <para><emphasis>The angel answered him, “I am Gabriel, who stands 
    in the presence of God, and I was sent to speak to you and to bring 
    you this good news. And now, because you did not believe my words, 
    which will be fulfilled in their time, you will be silent, unable 
    to speak, until the day these things take place.”</emphasis></para>
  </epigraph>
  <para>John the Baptist was to be the last prophet according to the 
  Old Testament pattern. His calling was to prepare peoples&apos; 
  hearts for Jesus to come.</para>
  <para>John was coming to a people who knew the Bible better than any 
  of their forefathers. They had large parts of their Bible memorized. 
  They had analyzed tiny details of the text&apos;s grammar for its 
  minute flavors of meaning.</para>
  <para>But they didn&apos;t <emphasis>know</emphasis> God. They had 
  replaced relationship with human knowledge.</para>
  <para>Zechariah was priest to God in the middle of this culture. 
  Unlike the bulk of the culture, he still believed--in the 
  abstract--that God could still work miracles. And he was praying for 
  a miracle: a son. Even though he and his wife were too old to have 
  children.</para>
  <para>Zechariah&apos;s name means <quote>memory of the Lord,</quote> 
  a fitting name for one of the few who was keeping alive the memory of 
  a God who is alive.</para>
  <sect1 id="section-id-for-hyperlinks">
    <title>Zechariah&apos;s obedience</title>
    <para>Zechariah had entered the temple to burn incense. Revelation 
    5:8 and 8:3-4 identify incense as a symbol of the prayers of 
    God&apos;s people.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had entered instead of another priest because the 
    Lord had revealed for him to be the one to serve through casting 
    lots.</para>
    <para>And in the Old Testament time, the Lord&apos;s presnce was in 
    the temple in a special way and there was a special blessing when 
    someone prayed to God in the temple.</para>
    <para>So Zechariah was praying in the Temple, in God&apos;s 
    presence. He was praying at a time God had revealed--when God spoke 
    through casting lots that he wanted Zechariah to come near and 
    pray.</para>
    <para>And Zechariah was about to find out, in the most dramatic way 
    possible, that he had been praying in God&apos;s will. Because God 
    had sent an angel to meet Zechariah in that place and to deliver 
    the message of God&apos;s promise of an answer.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>This was a (humanly) impossible task</title>
    <para>However, before such a child could</para>
    <para>According to human ability, this was impossible.</para>
    <para>Zechariah and Elizabeth were physically unable to bear 
    children.</para>
    <para>And they lived near the end of a corrupt priesthood that 
    elevated itself above the people. The Pharasees elevated themselves 
    as the <quote>true Bible teachers</quote> so much that they even 
    built a second ramp for themselves to walk up to the temple. Their 
    ramp separated them from the <quote>common people</quote> and was 
    physically elevated above the one the regular people had to walk on 
    to get up to the temple. The remains of this ramp are in Jerusalem 
    to this day.</para>
    <para>To raise a child as a priest in this environment who would 
    truly turn the people to God, and not to a superstar preacher or 
    musician (what the Pharasees were) was even more humanly impossible 
    than for Zechariah and Elizabeth to have a child to begin 
    with.</para>
    <para>But what is impossible with men is possible with God.</para>
    <para>John the Baptist <emphasis>was</emphasis> born and 
    <emphasis>did carry out</emphasis> this whole task that the Lord 
    gave him to do, though it cost him his very life.</para>
    <para>What man couldn&apos;t do due to human limitations was very 
    possible with God.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The answer</title>
    <para>The answer that God had promised was far beyond what 
    Zechariah had asked.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had just aske for a child. And God had provided 
    much more than any child. God promised a son who would carry the 
    inheritance forward.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had two kinds of inheritance to carry 
    forward:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Material</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Spiritual</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>Which was the Lord concerned most with?</para>
    <para>Naturally, the Lord was concerned with the spiritual.</para>
    <para />
  </sect1>
</chapter>
