<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter-last-supper-family-of-God">
	<title><quote>A lamb for each household</quote></title>
	
	<blockquote>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution><emphasis>Exodus 12:3 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
			
			<para><emphasis>Tell the whole community of Israel, ‘In the tenth day of this month they 
			each must take a lamb for themselves according to their families – a lamb for each 
			household.</emphasis></para>
		</epigraph>
		
		<epigraph>
			<attribution><emphasis>Matthew 26:19-20 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
			
			<para><emphasis>So the disciples did as Jesus had instructed them, and they prepared the 
			Passover.  When it was evening, he took his place at the table with the 
			twelve.</emphasis></para>
		</epigraph>
	</blockquote>
	
	<para>As we look at the above verses carefully, it appears that Jesus disobeyed what the
	Father revealed regarding how the Passover was to be celebrated.  Or did he?</para>
	
	<sect1 id="sect-faith-a-family-matter">
		<title>Faith, a family matter</title>
		
		<para>In the Old Testament, faith in God and fellowship with him is nearly always presented 
		in the context of a family.</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>God the Father with Adam and Eve in the garden.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Noah and the seven other family members who were saved on the Ark.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Lot and his family saved out of Sodom.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Abram and God's promise to give him a family and make his family a nation.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The <emphasis>children</emphasis> of Israel.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Pages and pages and pages of geneologies!</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The sons of Levi got to serve God in the temple and tabernacle.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The sons of Asaph, Heman, and Jeduthun led the worship in the temple.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The house of Israel, house of Jacob, house of David, house of Levi...</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Lists of families that returned to Jerusalem from the captivity in Babylon.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>...and on and on.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>In addition, the Jewish festivals were celebrated as family events.  In fact, in the
		Law of Moses, God <emphasis>specifically commanded</emphasis> for several of them&mdash;including 
		Passover, as noted in the verses quoted above&mdash;to be celebrated family by family.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="sect-the-last-passover-a-new-family-of-faith">
		<title>The last Passover, a new family of faith</title>
	
		<para>In the verses at the top, we see that Jesus told his disciples to prepare the Passover
		for all of them.  And then he sat down to eat the Passover with them.</para>
		
		<para>But God had spoken through Moses that "each must take a lamb for themselves according 
		to their families"  Thus, according to the Law of Moses, Jesus should have dismissed his
		disciples to all go to their families and celebrate Passover with them, and then
		to gather back together again later.</para>
		
		<para>But he didn't, because rather than fulfilling the Law according to the flesh, Jesus
		was going to fulfil the Law according to the Spirit, in a prophetic or symbolic sense.</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>God had told the people of Israel through Moses to "take a lamb according to 
				their families."</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>In a spiritual sense, the disciples were the family.  And Jesus was the 
				Lamb of God.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>The result is that what Jesus did was completely appropriate according to the Law of the
		Spirit of life.</para>
		
		<para>On the Passover day, the Lamb had to be killed and eaten.  Symbolically Jesus 
		fulfilled this also.</para>
	
		<blockquote>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Matthew 26:26-28 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
			
				<para><emphasis>While they were eating, Jesus took bread, and after giving thanks he broke it, 
				gave it to his disciples, and said, “Take, eat, this is my body.”  And after taking 
				the cup and giving thanks, he gave it to them, saying, “Drink from it, all of you, 
				for this is my blood, the blood of the covenant...”</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
		</blockquote>
		
		<para>After the meal, he finished fulfilling this prophesy.</para>
		
		<para>After the meal, Jesus--God's Lamb--got up from the table, walked to Calvary, and literally was 
		slain for our sins--so that we, too, could leave this world just as the Israelites
		left Egypt.</para>
	
		<blockquote>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Exodus 12:3 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
				
				<para><emphasis>Tell the whole community of Israel, ‘In the tenth day of this month they 
				each must take a lamb for themselves according to their families – a lamb for each 
				household.</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
		</blockquote>
		
		<para>Today Jesus invites believers to "do this in remembrance of him" and Paul adds
		that "as often as we eat this bread and drink this cup, we proclaim our Lord's death
		until he comes."  So today, too, we can eat this meal together.</para>
		
		<para>And when two or three of God's children are gathered together in his name,
		Jesus promises to be present today too (Matthew 18:20).  We again have God's family 
		assembled. We again have the Lamb.  We again have the supper.  And again, Jesus invites us
		to break the bread and share the cup--in remembrance of him.</para>

		<blockquote>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Exodus 12:3 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
				
				<para><emphasis>Tell the whole community of Israel, ‘In the tenth day of this month they 
				each must take a lamb for themselves according to their families – a lamb for each 
				household.</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
			
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Matthew 26:19-20 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
				
				<para><emphasis>So the disciples did as Jesus had instructed them, and they prepared the 
				Passover.  When it was evening, he took his place at the table with the 
				twelve.</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
		</blockquote>
		
	</sect1>
	
</chapter>
