<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter_harmony_of_last_supper">
	<title><quote>Do this in remembrance of me</quote></title>
	
	<epigraph>
		<attribution><emphasis>From 1 Corinthians 11:23-26</emphasis></attribution>
		
		<para><emphasis>“Do this in remembrance of me.”  .... For every time you eat 
		this bread and drink the cup, you proclaim the Lord’s death until he comes.</emphasis></para>
	</epigraph>
	
	<para><quote>Do this in remembrance of me.</quote></para>
	
	<para>What did Jesus want us to do in remembrance of him?  What are the implications of this for
	our understanding of the Body of Christ?  In order to really understand this,
	we must first look at exactly what Jesus and the disciples did that last supper.  Then we need
	to ask, <quote>What did the early disciples understand Jesus to mean?</quote></para>
	
	<para>The following	outline describes what happened, and was produced simply by harmonizing 
	what all of the Gospels and 1 Corinthians say about the Last Supper.</para>
	
	<sect1 id="section_harmony_of_last_supper1">
		<title>A harmony of the Last Supper</title>
		
		<para>
			<xi:include href="outline_supper_harmony.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>The Last Supper &mdash; A family meal</title>
		
		<para>As we look at the outline above, a few things should immediately strike us:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Broadly speaking, what we have is a picture or a description of a
				<emphasis>family meal</emphasis>, followed by a time of teaching by the
				<emphasis>head of the house</emphasis>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>This happened on the occasion of a Passover meal, yet, none of the details 
				of a Passover meal itself are described.  The meal description itself is
				generic.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>From the perspective of the disciples, the time of teaching was 
				<emphasis>unplanned</emphasis> and <emphasis>spontaneous</emphasis>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>When we look at this sequence of events a bit more closely, a few other
		things might strike us:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>At the beginning of the meal, Jesus invited the disciples to share
				the <quote>fruit of the vine</quote>, or in their culture, the wine.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>At the end of the meal, Jesus shared <quote>fruit of the vine</quote>
				<emphasis>again,</emphasis> immediately before he began the time of
				teaching.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>Since wine is the sort of beverage that one sips, rather than guzzling down
		a glass all at once, the reasonable expectation is that Jesus had them share the
		wine at the beginning of the meal, they sipped it throughout, and then he
		offered them a refill, as it were, to begin the time of teaching.</para>
		
		<para>But Jesus didn't stop there, the second time he divided the wine, Jesus
		did two things:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>He identified the wine with the new covenant in his own blood.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Just as he had with the bread, he commanded the disciples to
				<quote>Do this in remembrance of me.</quote></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>What did Jesus want the believers to do in remembrance of him?  The wine had
		been shared throughout a full meal.  Was that the context that Jesus intended or was
		he simply referring to the elements of he bread and the wine when he told us to
		<quote>Do this in remembrance of me</quote>?</para>
		
		<para>The easiest way to answer this question is to ask how the disciples themselves
		understood Jesus.  We are separated from him by around 2000 years, by language, by culture,
		etc.  But the disciples and early apostles had none of these impediments.  Let's start
		by looking at Paul's letter to the Corinthians.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Comparison to Paul's description of a church meeting</title>
		
		<para>In Paul's epistle to the Corinthians, Paul is addressing various problems in the
		Corinthian church, and as a result, describes how he wanted their meeting to be run.
		To begin, let's outline the topics that Paul covers when he discusses what to do
		<quote>When you come together</quote> in 1 Corinthians 11-14:</para>
		
		<table>
		  <title>The Love Feast in 1 Corinthians</title>
		  <tgroup cols="2">
		    <colspec colname="Corinthians" colwidth="1*"/>
		    <colspec colname="The Last Supper" colwidth="1*"/>
		    <thead>
		      <row>
				<entry>1 Corinthians</entry>
				<entry>The Last Supper</entry>
		      </row>
		    </thead>
		    <tbody>
		      <row>
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							The Lord's Supper as a full meal
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									The problem: Some over-ate and got drunk before their brothers even arrived (11:17-22)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Reminder of how Jesus instituted the meal (11:23-26)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Discerning the Lord's Body is part of healthy spiritual life (11:27-32)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Conclusion: If you're that hungry, eat a bit before you come to the Supper (11:33-34)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
				
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Start of the meal (Mk 14:17; Matt 26:20; Luke 22:14)
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus predicts his betrayal (Mk 14:18; Matt 26:21)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus says, "I have earnestly desired to eat this meal with you..." (Luke 22:14)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									“Fruit of the Vine” shared: "I will not drink of the fruit of the vine again until the Kingdom of God comes" (Luke 22:17-18)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
						<listitem><para>
							During the meal (Mk 14:22-24; Matt 26:26; 1Cor 11:23)
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus washes disciples' feet (John 13:1-17). 
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Bread broken; "This is my body which is broken for you" (Mk 14:22-24; Matt 26:26-29; Luke 22:17-18; 1 Cor 11:23-24); 
									Jesus says: "Do this in remembrance of me" (Luke 22:19, 1 Cor 11:23-24) 
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
		      </row>

		      <row>
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Spiritual Gifts connect the Head to the individual Members of the Body
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Introduction: What lifts Jesus up as Lord is from the Holy Spirit (12:1-3)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									The gifts are given to individuals for the benefit of all (12:4-7)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Different manifestations of the same Holy Spirit in different people (12:8-11)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									We are different members of the same Body (12:12-31)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
				
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							After the meal: Preparation for a time of teaching
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									“Fruit of the Vine” given to each individual AGAIN."The cup that is poured out is the new covenant in my blood" (Matt 14:24-25; Mk 26:27-28; Lk 22:20; 1 Cor 11:24)
									</para><para>
									(Wine given to each individual is a picture of the outpouring of the Holy Spirit because the wine
									is a symbol of the blood, and speaking spiritually, our life is the Holy Spirit, the blood of Jesus 
									flowing through the Body of Christ.) 
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									"Do this in remembrance of me" (1 Cor 11:23-24) 
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
		      </row>

		      <row>
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Love
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Gifts without love are just lifeless noise (13:1-7)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Gifts will cease when we see Jesus face to face but love never ends (13:8-13)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>

				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Jesus deals with the need for love in the Body
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus predicts his betrayal again! (Luke 22:21-38, Jn 13:18-30)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Disciples argue about who is greater (Luke 22:21-38)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus predicts Peter's denial (Luke 22:21-38, John 13:31-38)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
			  </row>

		      <row>
				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							When you come together, spiritual gifts enable Jesus to lead His Body
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Prefer to edify others when seeking tongues versus prophesy (14:1-19)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									The use of tongues and prophesy in evangelism (14:20-25)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									The order of service in an early church meeting (14:26-33a)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Women should remain under authority in the church (14:33b-36)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									This teaching is the Lord's command (14:37-38)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Summary on tongues / prophesy / orderliness (14:39-40)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>

				<entry valign="top">
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem><para>
							Jesus leads a time of teaching and prayer:
							<itemizedlist>
								<listitem><para>
									Vine/branches discourse (John 15 1-17)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									The World's hatred / promise of the Holy Spirit (John 15:18-16:18)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus tells about how he reveals the Father; overcomes the world (John 16:19-33)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									High priestly prayer (John 17)
								</para></listitem>
								<listitem><para>
									Jesus tells them to get money bag, traveling bag, cloak, swords (Luke 22:21-38)
								</para></listitem>
							</itemizedlist>
						</para></listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
				</entry>
		      </row>
		    </tbody>
		  </tgroup>
		</table>

		<para>When we line up the topics covered by Paul next to those covered by Jesus during the Last 
		Supper, one thing immediately jumps out at us: With the exception of the subject matter of Jesus's 
		final address, they used the <emphasis>exact same structure.</emphasis>  And regarding the subject matter
		of the teaching, Jesus had an actual teaching to give the disciples, but Paul was more concerned
		with telling the Corinthian church how to have a meeting where Jesus could continue to speak
		in the same manner as he had during the last supper.</para>
		
		<para>Is this a coincicence?</para>
		
		<para>This servant of the Lord finds it hard to believe that this is a coincidence.  It seems that
		Paul intentionally followed the form that Jesus had initiated when he had said, <emphasis>
		<quote>do this in rememberance of me.</quote></emphasis>  And if that weren't enough, Paul ends 
		his discourse with the following:
		
		<blockquote><para><emphasis>
			14:37 If anyone considers himself a prophet or spiritual person, he should acknowledge 
			that what I write to you is the Lord’s command. 14:38 If someone does not recognize this, he is 
			not recognized. (NET)
		</emphasis></para></blockquote></para>
		
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Conclusion</title>
		
		<para>Jesus had a full meal with the disciples during which he shared the bread and fruit of
		the vine.  Paul told the Corinthians how to hold a full meal in honor of Jesus that includes
		sharing the fruit of the vine.</para>
		
		<para>After supper, Jesus poured a second helping of the fruit of the vine, forshadowing the
		gifts of the Holy Spirit enabling each disciple to hear him individually.  Then he gave a teaching
		to the entire body of disciples.  Similarly, Paul described how Jesus, through the gifts of the Holy Spirit
		operating in love, desires to speak through individual in a particular way, so that when
		put together, the entire Body would be able to hear and understand Jesus teaching them.</para>
		
		<para>These two things were the essential ingredients for Jesus.  And they were the essential
		ingredients for Paul.  For Jesus, having these things was both necessary and also sufficient.  The
		same was true for Paul.</para>
		
		<para>Is it true for us?</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
