<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter_harmony_of_last_supper">
	<title><quote>Do this in remembrance of me</quote></title>
	
	<epigraph>
		<attribution><emphasis>Luke 22:17-20 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
		
		<para><emphasis>Then he took a cup, and after giving thanks he said, “Take this and 
		divide it among yourselves.  For I tell you that from now on I will not drink of the 
		fruit of the vine until the kingdom of God comes.”  Then he took bread, and after 
		giving thanks he broke it and gave it to them, saying, “This is my body which is 
		given for you.  Do this in remembrance of me.”  And in the same way he took the cup 
		after they had eaten, saying, “This cup that is poured out for you is the new 
		covenant in my blood.</emphasis></para>
	</epigraph>
	
	<para>What does Jesus want us to do in remembrance of him?  What are the implications of this for
	our understanding of the Body of Christ?  In order to really understand this,
	we must first look at exactly what Jesus and the disciples did that last supper.  Then we need
	to ask, <quote>What did the early disciples understand Jesus to mean?</quote></para>
	
	<para>The following	outline describes what happened, and was produced simply by harmonizing 
	what all of the Gospels and 1 Corinthians say about the Last Supper.</para>
	
	<sect1 id="section_harmony_of_last_supper1">
		<title>A harmony of the Last Supper</title>
		
		<para>
			<xi:include href="outline_supper_harmony.xml" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" />
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>What does Jesus want us to do to remember him?</title>
<!-- 		
		<para>As we examine at the outline above, here are a few things we might observe:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>Broadly speaking, what we have is a picture or a description of a
				<emphasis>family meal</emphasis>, followed by a time of teaching by the
				<emphasis>head of the house</emphasis>.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>From the perspective of the disciples, the time of teaching was 
				<emphasis>unplanned</emphasis> and <emphasis>spontaneous</emphasis>.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	 -->
		<para>When we examine this sequence of events, a few things might strike us:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>At the beginning of the meal, Jesus invited the disciples to share
				the <quote>fruit of the vine</quote>, or in their culture, the wine.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>At the end of the meal, Jesus shared <quote>fruit of the vine</quote>
				<emphasis>again,</emphasis> immediately before he began the time of
				teaching.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>Since wine is the sort of beverage that one sips, rather than guzzling down
		a glass all at once, the reasonable expectation is that Jesus had them share the
		wine at the beginning of the meal, they sipped it throughout, and then he
		offered them a refill, as it were, to begin the time of teaching.</para>
		
		<para>But Jesus didn't stop there, the second time he divided the wine, Jesus
		did two things:</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>He identified the wine with the new covenant in his own blood.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Just as he had with the bread, he commanded the disciples to
				<quote>Do this in remembrance of me.</quote></para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>What did Jesus want the believers to do in remembrance of him?  The wine had
		been shared throughout a full meal and the time of teaching afterward.  Was that the 
		context that Jesus intended or was he simply referring to the elements of he bread 
		and the wine when he told us to <quote>Do this in remembrance of me</quote>?</para>
		
		<para>One hint to the answer lies in comparing Matthew's and Luke's accounts of
		the Last Supper.  Matthew describes Jesus sharing the wine a single time, and
		associated with this, saying "I will not drink of the fruit of the vine again 
		until the Kingdom of God comes" (what Jesus said the <emphasis>first</emphasis>
		time), and "The cup that is poured out is the new covenant in my blood" (what
		Jesus said the <emphasis>second</emphasis> time he shared the cup.  So, to 
		Matthew, it seems that the sharing of the cup encompassed both the meal, and 
		the time of teaching afterward.</para>
		
		<para>What about the rest of Scripture?  Can we be reasonably sure that this
		understanding is accurate?</para>
		
		<para>The easiest way to answer this question is to ask how the disciples themselves
		understood Jesus.  We are separated from him by around 2000 years, by language, by culture,
		etc.</para>
		
		<para>But the disciples and early apostles had none of these impediments.  They were
		ideally situated to understand exactly what Jesus intended.</para>
		
		<para>That will be the topic of our next study.</para>
		
	</sect1>
	
</chapter>
