<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-jbaptist_birth">
  <title>For your prayer has been heard</title>
  <epigraph>
    <attribution><emphasis>Luke 1:13</emphasis></attribution>
    <para><emphasis>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has 
    been heard.</emphasis></para>
  </epigraph>
  <para>During the time of Zechariah, the spiritual situation in Israel 
  was dire.</para>
  <para>The religious leaders knew the Bible better than any of their 
  forefathers. They had large parts of their Bible memorized. Some had 
  memorized the whole thing. They had analyzed tiny details of the 
  Bible&apos;s grammar in its original language for its minute flavors 
  of meaning. They were very zealous for the traditions that had been 
  handed down to them.</para>
  <para>But when the wise men came looking for Jesus, following the 
  star, none of Bible scholars of the day could be bothered to follow 
  up on the wise mens&apos; report that their Messiah had been born, 
  even though they knew from the Scriptures where he would be found. 
  Although all of the signs that their Messiah was about to come had 
  already been fulfilled, most had stopped watching and waiting for his 
  appearing.</para>
  <para>Except for a tiny minority (Simeon, Anna), the people had also 
  forgotten how to hear God&apos;s voice and to walk in 
  <emphasis>relationship</emphasis> with him.</para>
  <para>They didn&apos;t really <emphasis>know God.</emphasis> They 
  just knew <emphasis>about him.</emphasis></para>
  <para>The result was that they had replaced the loving, caring, 
  family relationship that God had intended for his people to have with 
  him with mere human knowledge and religious ritual.</para>
  <para>This situation was a great difficulty for the people of Israel. 
  Because, they knew about God, but they didn&apos;t <emphasis>know 
  him,</emphasis> how would they recognize God in human form?  Again, 
  how would they recognize him when he humbled himself, taking the form 
  of a man, and became obedient even to death on the cross?</para>
  <para>But God had a plan.</para>
  <sect1 id="section-id-for-hyperlinks">
    <title>God chose Zechariah to help solve this problem</title>
    <para>Zechariah was priest to God in the middle of this culture. 
    Unlike most in his culture, he still believed--in his mind at 
    least--that God could still speak and could still work miracles. 
    And he was praying for a miracle: a son, even though he and his 
    wife were too old to have children.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had entered the temple to burn incense. Revelation 
    5:8 and 8:3-4 identify incense as a symbol of the prayers of 
    God&apos;s people.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had entered the temple to pray instead of another 
    priest because the Lord had revealed for him to do so through 
    casting lots <emphasis><quote>according to the custom of the 
    priesthood</quote></emphasis> (v8).</para>
    <para>And Zechariah was about to find out, in the most dramatic way 
    possible, that he had been praying in God&apos;s will.</para>
    <para>God sent an angel to meet Zechariah in that place and to 
    deliver the message of God&apos;s promise of an answer.</para>
    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis><quote>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your 
      prayer has been heard.</quote></emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The answer</title>
    <para>The answer that God had promised was far beyond what 
    Zechariah had asked.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had just asked for a child. And God had provided 
    much more than any child. God promised a son who would carry 
    Israel&apos;s spiritual inheritance forward. Who would turn 
    Israel&apos;s hearts back to a <emphasis>relationship with 
    God.</emphasis> They needed to be prepared because they were living 
    in the time just before Jesus, Immanuel, God With Us was about to 
    come.</para>
    <para>Naturally, the Lord was concerned with the material blessing. 
    A flesh-and-blood son would carry forward Zechariah&apos;s family 
    inheritance and take away his social stigma from being 
    childless.</para>
    <para>But the Lord was far more concerned with who this son would 
    be spiritually:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>What would he do?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>How would he live?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>What would his life mean?</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>What spiritual inheritance, what spiritual legacy would 
        he leave?</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This entire experience of having no son had been a great 
    difficulty for Zechariah. But God was about to turn 
    Zechariah&apos;s difficulty into an answer for all of God&apos;s 
    people&apos;s needs.</para>
    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis><quote>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your 
      prayer has been heard.</quote></emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Forerunner before the Lord</title>
    <para>John&apos;s spiritual legacy was to be the forerunner before 
    Jesus, to <quote><emphasis>make ready for the Lord a people 
    prepared for him.</emphasis></quote></para>
    <para>They needed their hearts prepared so that when Jesus came, as 
    many as possible would be ready to believe him, to receive his 
    word, and to follow him. This had two parts:</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>Zechariah&apos;s child had to be prepared to deliver 
      God&apos;s message</title>
      <para>Before God could use John to turn other peoples&apos; 
      hearts to God, John&apos;s own heart had to belong to God. But 
      God had promised Zechariah a special provision. His son 
      would:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from before 
          birth</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Avoid wine or strong drink. In this context, wine is a 
          symbol of being addicted to this world&apos;s 
          pleasures.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Be great in the <emphasis>sight of the Lord</emphasis> 
          (as opposed to the sight of man)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>These were the qualifications that God was going to give 
      John the Baptist to enable him to make ready for the Lord a 
      people prepared for him.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2>
      <title>This was an (humanly) impossible task</title>
      <para>This was an impossible task, both for Zechariah and for 
      John.</para>
      <para>Zechariah had aged, both physically and spiritually.</para>
      <para>Physically, he and his wife were too old to have children. 
      And he had aged spiritually also. Although his mind still 
      believed in a living God who hears his people and works miracles, 
      his heart had stopped believing. Both of these difficulties 
      needed addressing, and humanly speaking, both are impossible to 
      address.</para>
      <para>But what is impossible for man is possible for God. God was 
      about to do two miracles for Zechariah:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>To give Zechariah a physical son. To answer 
          Zechariah&apos;s immediate prayer.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>But more than that, God was about to change 
          Zechariah&apos;s heart. Zechariah would no longer have a 
          spiritually aged heart of unbelief but would have a fresh, 
          young, vibrant heart of faith, full of the Holy Spirit. This 
          was God&apos;s provision for Zechariah to be able to raise 
          John in a manner so that John could fulfill the prophesies 
          about him.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Having a baby is one thing. Bringing a baby home is another 
      thing. But raising a baby into an adult who walks with God and 
      chooses God&apos;s ways over man&apos;s ways is an even greater 
      miracle. Having a child who would grow up to be like John the 
      Baptist is one of the greatest miracles of all.</para>
      <para>As a result, through Zechariah--through Zechariah&apos;s 
      prayers--God was going to prepare his people for Jesus to 
      come.</para>
      <blockquote>
        <para><emphasis><quote>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your 
        prayer has been heard.</quote></emphasis></para>
      </blockquote>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Your prayer has been heard</title>
    <para>Today, we live near the end of church history. The 
    institutional Western church has aged and is no longer producing 
    spiritual children able to transform our culture. Institutional 
    church attendance is declining and peoples&apos; hearts are growing 
    progressively colder.</para>
    <para>The dominant Christian culture elevates Bible teachers who 
    are trained in a certain way above all of the people. These 
    teachers memorize large parts of the Bible and study the minute 
    details of the original language for its shades of meaning.</para>
    <para>A result is that people have a lot of head knowledge about 
    God, but few <emphasis>know God in a healthy family-style intimate 
    love relationship.</emphasis> (Only this kind of <emphasis>love 
    relationship</emphasis> with God is a proper motive to study the 
    Bible that way.)</para>
    <para>We, too, live in the time immediately before Jesus is about 
    to come; the Lord is again calling to himself a people prepared for 
    him.</para>
    <sect2>
      <title>You will have a child</title>
      <para>We too have an impossible task: Like Zechariah, the Lord 
      has called <emphasis>us</emphasis> to bear and raise spiritual 
      children. Spiritual children who, like John the Baptist:</para>
      <para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from 
            (before) their spiritual birth</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Will not drink the wine of this world&apos;s 
            pleasures</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Will be great in the <emphasis>sight of the 
            Lord</emphasis> (as opposed to the sight of man)</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Will continue the task of turning many more of 
            God&apos;s chosen people to the Lord their God</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>Will go as <emphasis>forerunner before the Lord...to 
            make ready for the Lord a people prepared for 
            him</emphasis></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>He has called us to do this because, just as in 
      Zechariah&apos;s day, Jesus is about to come.</para>
      <para>We cannot do this task in our own ability. It is a humanly 
      impossible task both to bear spiritual children, and to raise 
      them to spiritual maturity so that they fulfill these 
      things.</para>
      <para>Just like Zechariah, we can only pray that God would give 
      us these children. And like Zechariah, it is through prayer that 
      these spiritual children are bought to maturity.</para>
      <para>And like Zechariah, the Lord sends his angel to announce 
      that our prayers are according to God&apos;s will. That the Lord 
      will provide, just as he said.</para>
      <para>
        <blockquote>
          <para><emphasis><quote>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your 
          prayer has been heard.</quote></emphasis></para>
        </blockquote>
      </para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
