<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter-last-supper-family-of-God">
	<title><quote>A lamb for each household</quote></title>
	
	<blockquote>
		<epigraph>
			<attribution><emphasis>Exodus 12:3 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
			
			<para><emphasis>Tell the whole community of Israel, ‘In the tenth day of this month they 
			each must take a lamb for themselves according to their families – a lamb for each 
			household.</emphasis></para>
		</epigraph>
		
		<epigraph>
			<attribution><emphasis>Matthew 26:19-20 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
			
			<para><emphasis>So the disciples did as Jesus had instructed them, and they prepared the 
			Passover.  When it was evening, he took his place at the table with the 
			twelve.</emphasis></para>
		</epigraph>
	</blockquote>
	
	<para>As we look at the above verses carefully, it appears that Jesus disobeyed what the
	Father revealed regarding how the Passover was to be celebrated.  Or did he?</para>
	
	<sect1 id="sect-faith-a-family-matter">
		<title>Faith, a family matter</title>
		
		<para>In the Old Testament, faith in God and fellowship with him is nearly always presented 
		in the context of a family.</para>
		
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>God the Father with Adam and Eve in the garden.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Noah and the seven other family members who were saved on the Ark.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Lot and his family saved out of Sodom.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Abram and God's promise to give him a family and make his family a nation.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The <emphasis>children</emphasis> of Israel.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The sons of Levi got to serve God in the temple and tabernacle.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The sons of Asaph, Heman, and Jeduthun led the worship in the temple.</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>The house of Israel, house of Jacob, house of David, house of Levi...</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>...and on and on.</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>In addition, the Jewish festivals were celebrated as family events.  In fact, in the
		Law of Moses, God <emphasis>specifically commanded</emphasis> for several of them&mdash;including 
		Passover, as noted in the verses quoted above&mdash;to be celebrated family by family.</para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="sect-the-last-passover-a-new-family-of-faith">
		<title>The last Passover, a new family of faith</title>
	
		<para>In the verses at the top, we see that Jesus told his disciples to prepare the Passover
		for all of them.  And then he sat down to eat the Passover with them.</para>
		
		<para>But God had spoken through Moses that the Passover was to be eaten "according to
		their families."  According to the Law of Moses, Jesus should have dismissed his
		disciples to all go to their families and celebrate Passover with them, and then
		to gather back together again later.</para>
		
		<para>But he didn't, because he had something very special to accomplish:</para>
	
		<blockquote>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution>Matthew 26:26-28 &net;</attribution>
			
				<para>While they were eating, Jesus took bread, and after giving thanks he broke it, 
				gave it to his disciples, and said, “Take, eat, this is my body.”  And after taking 
				the cup and giving thanks, he gave it to them, saying, “Drink from it, all of you, 
				for this is my blood, the blood of the covenant...</para>
			</epigraph>
		</blockquote>
		
		<para>After eating the bread and drinking the cup, the bread and the fruit of the vine 
		literally became a part of each disciple.  In the words of Adam, then, the disciples
		spiritually were "bone of my bones and flesh of my flesh", the Body of Christ,
		taken out of his side.</para>
		
		<para>Jesus had worked a miracle.  The Law commanded that they meet together
		as a family to celebrate Passover.  Jesus had just created a new family, the Family of God.
		It was some days before this family became known as the ekklesia, the assembly, the
		Church.</para>
		
		<para>At the beginning, it was just a family&mdash;eating a meal together, listening to the
		head of the house instruct them in the way they should go.</para>
	
		<blockquote>
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Exodus 12:3 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
				
				<para><emphasis>Tell the whole community of Israel, ‘In the tenth day of this month they 
				each must take a lamb for themselves according to their families – a lamb for each 
				household.</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
			
			<epigraph>
				<attribution><emphasis>Matthew 26:19-20 &net;</emphasis></attribution>
				
				<para><emphasis>So the disciples did as Jesus had instructed them, and they prepared the 
				Passover.  When it was evening, he took his place at the table with the 
				twelve.</emphasis></para>
			</epigraph>
		</blockquote>
	</sect1>
	
</chapter>
