<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-jbaptist_birth">
  <title>To make ready for the Lord a people prepared for him</title>
  <epigraph>
    <attribution><emphasis>Luke 1:13</emphasis></attribution>
    <para><emphasis>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer has 
    been heard.</emphasis></para>
  </epigraph>
  <para>John the Baptist was to be the last prophet according to the 
  Old Testament pattern. He came as prophesied in Malachi 4:5 and other 
  places in the Old Testament <quote>in the spirit and power of Elijah, 
  to turn the hearts of the fathers back to their children and the 
  disobedient to the wisdom of the just.</quote></para>
  <para>John was coming to a people who knew the Bible better than any 
  of their forefathers. They had large parts of their Bible memorized. 
  Some had memorized the whole thing. They had analyzed tiny details of 
  the Bible&apos;s grammar in its original language for its minute 
  flavors of meaning. They were very zealous for the traditions that 
  had been handed down to them.</para>
  <para>When the wise men came looking for Jesus, following the star, 
  none of Bible scholars of the day could be bothered to follow up on 
  the wise mens&apos; report that their Messiah had been born, even 
  though they knew from the Scriptures where he would be found. 
  Although all of the signs that their Messiah was about to come had 
  already been fulfilled, most had stopped watching and waiting for his 
  appearing.</para>
  <para>Except for a tiny minority (Simeon, Anna), they didn&apos;t 
  know how to hear God&apos;s voice.</para>
  <para>They had replaced relationship with human knowledge and 
  religious ritual.</para>
  <para>They didn&apos;t really <emphasis>know God.</emphasis></para>
  <sect1>
    <title>To prepare the way of the Lord</title>
    <para>This situation was a great difficulty for the people of 
    Israel. They knew about God, but they didn&apos;t <emphasis>know 
    him.</emphasis> But Jesus, their Messiah was about to come, and how 
    would they recognize God in human form if they didn&apos;t know God 
    to begin with?</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="section-id-for-hyperlinks">
    <title>Zechariah&apos;s obedience</title>
    <para>Zechariah was priest to God in the middle of this culture. 
    Unlike most in his culture, he still believed--in his mind at 
    least--that God could still speak and could still work miracles. 
    And he was praying for a miracle: a son, even though he and his 
    wife were too old to have children.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had entered the temple to burn incense. Revelation 
    5:8 and 8:3-4 identify incense as a symbol of the prayers of 
    God&apos;s people.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had entered the temple to pray instead of another 
    priest because the Lord had revealed for him to do so through 
    casting lots <quote><emphasis>according to the custom of the 
    priesthood</emphasis></quote> (v8).</para>
    <para>So Zechariah was praying in the Temple, in God&apos;s 
    presence. He was praying at a time God had revealed--when God spoke 
    through casting lots that he wanted Zechariah to come near and 
    pray.</para>
    <para>And Zechariah was about to find out, in the most dramatic way 
    possible, that he had been praying in God&apos;s will. Because God 
    had sent an angel to meet Zechariah in that place and to deliver 
    the message of God&apos;s promise of an answer.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The answer</title>
    <para>The answer that God had promised was far beyond what 
    Zechariah had asked.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had just asked for a child. And God had provided 
    much more than any child. God promised a son who would carry 
    Israel&apos;s spiritual inheritance forward. Who would turn 
    Israel&apos;s hearts back to a <emphasis>relationship with 
    God.</emphasis> They needed to be prepared because they were living 
    in the time just before Jesus, Immanuel, God With Us was about to 
    come.</para>
    <para>Naturally, the Lord was concerned with the material blessing. 
    A flesh-and-blood son would carry forward Zechariah&apos;s family 
    inheritance and take away his social stigma from being 
    childless.</para>
    <para>But the Lord was far more concerned with who this son would 
    be spiritually. What he would do. How he would live. What his life 
    would mean. What <emphasis>spiritual inheritance</emphasis>, what 
    spiritual legacy he would leave.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Forerunner before the Lord</title>
    <para>John&apos;s spiritual legacy was to be the forerunner before 
    Jesus, to <quote><emphasis>make ready for the Lord a people 
    prepared for him.</emphasis></quote>.</para>
    <para>They needed their hearts prepared so that when Jesus came, as 
    many as possible would be ready to believe him, to receive his 
    word, and to follow him. This has several components:</para>
    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis>He will turn many of the people of Israel to the 
      Lord their God.</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
    <para>To be turned <emphasis>to God</emphasis> first requires that 
    our affections be turned <emphasis>away from all other 
    things.</emphasis> For example, they needed to no longer have the 
    following sorts of things rule their affections::</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Amusements and worldly pleasure as a primary goal in 
          their lives</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Religious works motivated from a desire to please 
          one&apos;s self</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Philosophy, including theology, as an end in 
          itself</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>To be turned to God means to have one&apos;s focus, 
    attention, and desire fixed on God above all of these other things. 
    To change one&apos;s prioirites foremost to a passionate love 
    pursuit of God.</para>
    <para>The person who could accomplish these tasks needed some 
    special qualifications:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To be great in the <emphasis>sight of the Lord</emphasis> 
        (as opposed to the sight of man)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To avoid wine or strong drink.  In this context, wine is 
        a symbol of this world&apos;s pleasures.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from (before) 
        their spiritual birth</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>The name <emphasis>John</emphasis> means <emphasis><quote>the 
    grace or mercy of the Lord</quote></emphasis> -- this is the only 
    way our hearts can be turned back to the Lord.</para>
    <para>This was John&apos;s function: to proclaim God&apos;s grace 
    and mercy. To invite people out of a system of theology, head 
    knowledge, and works and back into a 
    <emphasis>relationship</emphasis> with God through the one who 
    would follow--that is, though Jesus.</para>
    <para>The only thing required of people was for them to 
    <emphasis>repent,</emphasis> to tell God they were sorry for trying 
    to live life by themselves according to ideas, rules, and 
    regulations. Instead, they simply needed to receive God&apos;s free 
    love, grace, and forgiveness begin to choose a <emphasis>love 
    relationship</emphasis> with him.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>This was an (humanly) impossible task</title>
    <para>This was an impossible task, both for Zechariah and for 
    John.</para>
    <para>Zechariah had aged, both physically and spiritually.</para>
    <para>Physically, he and his wife were too old to have children.  
    And spiritually, although his mind still believed in a living God 
    who hears his people and works miracles, his heart had stopped 
    believing.  Both of these difficulties needed addressing, and 
    humanly speaking, both are impossible to address.</para>
    <para>But what is impossible for man is possible for God.</para>
    <para>God was about to do two miracles for Zechariah:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>To give Zechariah a physical son.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>To change Zechariah&apos;s heart from a spiritually aged 
        heart of unbelief to a fresh, young, vibrant heart of faith, 
        full of the Holy Spirit.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>And through Zechariah, God was going to birth one who 
    would:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Be great in the <emphasis>sight of the Lord</emphasis> 
        (as opposed to the sight of man)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Not drink the wine of this world&apos;s pleasures</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from (before) 
        birth</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Continue the task of turning many more of God&apos;s 
        chosen people to the Lord their God</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Go as <emphasis>forerunner before the Lord...to make 
        ready for the Lord a people prepared for him</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>The Church has a similar function</title>
    <para>Today, we live in a similar spiritual situation.</para>
    <para>The dominant Christian culture elevates Bible teachers who 
    are trained in a certain way above all of the people. These 
    teachers memorize large parts of the Bible and study the minute 
    details of the original language for its shades of meaning.</para>
    <para>A result is that people have a lot of head knowledge about 
    God, but few <emphasis>know God in a love relationship.</emphasis> 
    Only a <emphasis>love relationship</emphasis> with God is a proper 
    motive to study the Bible that way.</para>
    <para>And today, the Lord still wants to raise up a people with a 
    prophetic function: to <emphasis>to make ready for the Lord a 
    people prepared for him.</emphasis> Because Jesus is coming 
    again.</para>
    <para>The first time, Jesus came as the lamb to be slain. Next time 
    He will come as the Lion of Judah, the conquering king.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1>
    <title>Your prayer has been heard</title>
    <para>Today, we live near the end of church history. The 
    institutional Western church has aged and is no longer producing 
    spiritual children able to transform our culture. Institutional 
    church attendance in the decline and peoples&apos; hearts are 
    growing progressively colder.</para>
    <para>But Jesus is coming. And the Lord has called to himself a 
    people prepared for him.</para>
    <para>We too have an impossible task: Like Zechariah, the Lord has 
    called <emphasis>us</emphasis> to bear these spiritual children. 
    Spiritual children who, like John the Baptist:</para>
    <para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will be great in the <emphasis>sight of the 
          Lord</emphasis> (as opposed to the sight of man)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will not drink the wine of this world&apos;s 
          pleasures</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will be filled with the Holy Spirit, even from (before) 
          their spiritual birth</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will continue the task of turning many more of 
          God&apos;s chosen people to the Lord their God</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Will go as <emphasis>forerunner before the Lord...to 
          make ready for the Lord a people prepared for 
          him</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>Similar to Zechariah, we cannot do this task in our own 
    ability.</para>
    <para>Just like Zechariah, we can only pray that God would give us 
    these children.</para>
    <para>And like Zechariah, the Lord sends his angel to announce that 
    our prayers are according to God&apos;s will. That these prayers 
    are heard. And that as we are faithful, the Lord will provide, just 
    as he said.</para>
    <para>
      <blockquote>
        <para><emphasis>Do not be afraid, Zechariah, for your prayer 
        has been heard.</emphasis></para>
      </blockquote>
    </para>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
