<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="chapter-jbaptist_birth">
  <title>The University of Silence</title>
  <epigraph>
    <attribution><emphasis>Luke 1:19-20</emphasis></attribution>
    <para><emphasis>Zechariah said to the angel, “How can I be sure of 
    this? For I am an old man, and my wife is old as well.” The angel 
    answered him, “I am Gabriel, who stands in the presence of God, and 
    I was sent to speak to you and to bring you this good 
    news.”</emphasis></para>
  </epigraph>
  <para>Jesus was about to come to Israel, to a nation that by and 
  large had forgotten God&apos;s promise to bring a deliverer.  Or they 
  had changed him into a deliverer in their own image: one who would 
  deliver them from the Romans.</para>
  <para>God needed to raise up a man who would help people to see the 
  real Jesus.</para>
  <para>But all men start out as little boys.  So God&apos;s first task 
  was to prepare a man, one in this culture of academic religion, to 
  raise this little boy--to become John the Baptist.</para>
  <para>John needed to be the sort of man who could hear God&apos;s 
  voice and be a prophet to his people.</para>
  <para>John needed a daddy who could hear God&apos;s voice and be a 
  prophet to him first.  He needed a family where he could be nurtured 
  and could grow into the kind of <emphasis>man</emphasis> that God 
  wanted for him to be.</para>
  <para>There was one problem.  The man who God had prepared to raise 
  John the Baptist had given up believing that God could speak, that 
  God could work miracles--at least miracles for him.</para>
  <para>So God first confirmed through casting lots among the other 
  priests that Zechariah was to serve him in the temple.</para>
  <para>Many times when God wants to use us in some way, he begins by 
  confirming this in an objective way through other people who love 
  him.</para>
  <para>But this wasn&apos;t enough for Zechariah.</para>
  <para>Next, God sent Gabriel the angel to Zechariah.  The appearance 
  of the angel must have been magestic and awe-inspiring, because the 
  Bible says that Zechariah was visibly shaken when he saw then angel 
  and seized with fear.</para>
  <para>Even this wasn&apos;t enough for Zechariah.</para>
  <para>Then the angel delivered his message--that God was going to 
  give Zechariah a son.  </para>
  <para>But even this wasn&apos;t enough.</para>
  <para>
    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis>Zechariah said to the angel, “How can I be sure 
      of this? For I am an old man, and my wife is old as well.” The 
      angel answered him, “I am Gabriel, who stands in the presence of 
      God, and I was sent to speak to you and to bring you this good 
      news.”</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
  </para>
  <para>Fortunately, God had a cure for Zechariah&apos;s 
  unbelief:</para>
  <para>
    <blockquote>
      <para><emphasis>now, because you did not believe my words, which 
      will be fulfilled in their time,61 you will be silent, unable to 
      speak, until the day these things take place. 
      (v20)</emphasis></para>
    </blockquote>
  </para>
  <para>When Zechariah left the temple, he not only was unable to 
  speak, but since people had to motion to him to communicate, it seems 
  that he was also unable to hear.</para>
  <para>What had been true of Zechariah spiritually was now true of him 
  physically.  He had been unable to hear the good news from the angel, 
  and now he could not hear what anybody said.  He had been unable to 
  believe, and thus unable to speak with faith the prophesy the Lord 
  had given him, and thus he was also unable to speak.</para>
  <para>But as if this weren&apos;t enough, at this point, everybody 
  else but Zechariah gets to hear the Lord speak and to prophesy his 
  words.</para>
  <para>Mary receives a visit from the angel, receives the word of the 
  Lord and believes it.  Next thing we know, Mary is visiting Elizabeth 
  and before we know it both are filled with the Holy Spirit and are 
  prophesying.</para>
  <para>And Zechariah simply gets to watch it all happen but not 
  receive any of it for himself!</para>
  <para>How his heart must have yearned to have another chance to hear 
  the angel&apos;s voice!  How he must have desired to be able to speak 
  with his own voice, &quot;We are having a son, and his name will be 
  John!&quot;</para>
  <para>But he couldn&apos;t.  And so the desire to hear and to speak 
  undoubtedly grew in his heart--until the 8th day after John had been 
  born and God&apos;s word had been fulfilled.</para>
  <para>That day, there was a commotion about what to name the child.  
  All of the people in the world wanted to name him according to his 
  earthly father&apos;s name.  But at the right time, the writing 
  tablet was given to Zechariah, and he wrote, &quot;His name is 
  John!&quot;</para>
  <para>And then Zechariah again heard God&apos;s voice, and delivered 
  God&apos;s word in a beautiful prophesy to the people!</para>
  <para>God had transformed Zechariah from one who was righteous before 
  him, but whose faith was weak, into one who heard God&apos;s voice, 
  spoke God&apos;s word, and obeyed with expectency.</para>
  <para>Sometimes we, too, suffer from periods of dryness.  Like 
  Zechariah&apos;s, they may stem from unbelief, but that may not be 
  the only reason.  But frequently God is allowing these times of 
  silence as a kind of university--to deepen our desire to pursue him 
  above all else.</para>
  <para>When we emerge from these times, God gives us a new revelation 
  of himself, of the work he has for us to do.  And God puts new words 
  in our mouth: words of praise, adoration, and direction.</para>
  <para>Because ultimately:</para>
  <para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>God wants us to have a love relationship with him, not 
        just beliefs about him.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>God wants to use us to raise up the spiritual children 
        who will teach others to know God.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Just as Zechariah&apos;s family was how God raised the 
        first &quot;John the Baptist&quot;, family-style relationships 
        are how we grow up to maturity in anything, including in our 
        relationshp with God.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </para>
  <para>May God see fit to use us to raise up a new generation of 
  &quot;John the Baptists&quot; to prepare the way of the Lord.</para>
  <para>Because Jesus is coming again, and the world needs to be 
  prepared for him.</para>
</chapter>
