<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter_discerning_the_body">
	<title>The importance of discerning the Body</title>
	
	<epigraph>
		<attribution><emphasis>1 Corinthians 11:23, 29-30, NET</emphasis></attribution>
		
		<para><emphasis>For I received from the Lord what I also passed on to you, that 
		the Lord Jesus on the night in which he was betrayed took bread, and after he 
		had given thanks he broke it and said, “This is my body, which is for you. Do this 
		in remembrance of me.”....</emphasis></para>
		
		<para><emphasis>For the one who eats and drinks without careful 
		regard for the body eats and drinks judgment against himself.  That is why many 
		of you are weak and sick, and quite a few are dead.</emphasis></para>
	</epigraph>
	
	<para>In our text, the word translated as "without careful regard" more literally
	means “judging between, recognizing, distinguishing.”</para>
	
	<para>Then Paul, after describing the parable of the Body that Jesus gave us during
	the Last Supper, goes on to say quite a radical thing: essentially <quote>If you 
	aren't recognizing, distinguishing, and carefully regarding the Lord's Body, you
	could be sick spiritually, and might even die spiritually.</quote></para>
	
	<para>Consequently, for a topic so important, one would think that the New Testament would
	have plenty of direct teaching on the topic, yet there appears to be very little
	taught in the New Testament except in parables.</para>
	
	<para>So, what exactly <emphasis>is</emphasis> the Body of Christ?  Here we will
	attempt to list, catalog, and attempt to understand the language of types and
	metaphors the Lord gives us in the Bible that describe what is the Body of Christ.
	This chapter will serve as an introduction, and subsequent chapters will examine
	details.</para>
	
	<sect1 id="section_body_is_bread">
		<title>And Jesus took bread..., broke it and said <quote>This is my body...</quote></title>
		
		<para></para>
	</sect1>
	
	<sect1 id="section-body_is_family">
		<title>The Body as the Family of God</title>
		
		<para></para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
