<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN" 
  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
	<!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local-entities.ent">
	%local; 
]>

<chapter id="chapter-id-for-hyperlinks">
	<title>Chapter Title</title>
	
	<epigraph>
		<attribution><emphasis></emphasis></attribution>
		<para><emphasis></emphasis></para>
	</epigraph>
	
	<para>Say something about what this chapter will say.</para>
	
	<sect1 id="section-id-for-hyperlinks">
		<title>Section title</title>
		
		<para>bla bla bla.</para>
		
		
I have two general concerns regarding church life and relationships that in practice seem to be in tension.
My desire to, as the Baptists say, have the Bible be "the only rule of faith and practice".
At the same time, to see Christ's Body "all attain to the unity of the faith and of the knowledge of the Son of God" (Eph 4:13), and "that they will all be one, just as you, Father, are in me and I am in you." (John 17:21)
How does one reconcile these two things: having a high personal standard/integrity, yet to be really, truly unified with ALL other believers--to be one just as the Father is in the Son and the Son is in the Father?

The only way I can imagine this working is:
To maintain a high personal standard, but recognizing that where I may spiritually recognize some things, others see other things; to always be striving to learn from others.
To understand, apply, and practice Christ's standard, rule, and means for fellowship with all other true believers.
It is with #2 that I've become concerned--because until we understand how Jesus intends for us to come to the "unity of the faith", we cannot fulfill Ephesians 4 nor John 17

"you gave to me I have given to them, that they may be one just as we are one – I in them and you in me – that they may be completely one, so that the world will know that you sent me, and you have loved them just as you have loved me."

Another way of asking the same question:  What is the minimal standard of fellowship with other believers, as revealed in the Bible?

Many churches have tried to follow the slogan, "In essentials unity, in non-essentials liberty, in all things charity".  But, as you have observed to me in the past, this tends to get bogged down deciding on what is the boundary between essentials and non-essentials.

To me, a key insight has been that Jesus and Paul (compared to us) set a very low standard on how corporate worship should be conducted.  To them, corporate worship was simply a family meal (including the breaking of bread) followed by a time of seeking to hear from the Lord together.

I note that every believer I've ever known already has this same standard, except that (because of church tradition) we have stripped the Lord's Supper out of the supper.

Among your College Church friends, I observe that you already meet like this.

We do this already with our believing neighbors on the block; with believing friends who I've met at Caribou, etc...

The main area I could imagine we could improve is to put the Lord's Supper back into our intimate gatherings, just as Jesus did, as Paul encouraged in Corinthians, and as is recorded that Paul did in the book of Acts.

The rest--e.g.: formal "services" descended from Roman imperial court ceremonies, etc..., well, the Bible doesn't talk about that and if you find them useful go ahead and do them--but they aren't a requirement in Scripture.

I personally have found this very freeing.

And I think that if believers all over understood this, it would blow up the power of the denominational system that currently divides us according to our traditions and cultural preferences.

It would finally give us a chance to fulfill what Jesus prayed for us the night he went to the cross: that we would be one as he and the Father are one.

Because at one level, being one simply means to be a part of the same spiritual family--where "blood is thicker than water" and though we might have differences, we can still get together for a meal and prayer and love each other anyway.  The Holy Spirit and the Blood cover our differences, weaknesses, and sin.

The one small thing currently missing from our practice is easy enough to replace--even if visitors are present--by including a simple explanation and reading the Word: breaking the bread and sharing the cup.

In fact, I was going to request that when we get together for Thanksgiving dinner, that we break bread together and share the fruit of the vine together.  We already do everything else Jesus taught; we might as well do this too--and be one Body even as we share together as one family.  And what better way to give thanks than to commemorate our Lord's death together until he returns?

	</sect1>
</chapter>
